Guide to the George A. Romero Archival Collection, 1962-2017 SC.2019.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
George A. Romero Archival Collection
1962-2017
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Romero, George A.
SC.2019.03
100 boxes
George Andrew Romero (1940-2017) was an American filmmaker and author, best known for horror films produced in Pittsburgh and the surrounding areas. Romero wrote and directed feature films, television, industrial films, and commercials. He also wrote comic books, a children's book, short stories, and a novel. The collection documents his career as a filmmaker and writer, with manuscripts and production materials for both produced and unproduced projects, promotional materials, press clippings, legal documents, photographs, film and video, and correspondence. NOTE: ONLY THE MANUSCRIPT MATERIAL, PRINTED PHOTOGRAPHS, AND PROPS FROM THE COLLECTION ARE FULLY PROCESSED AND AVAILABLE FOR RESEARCH AT THE PRESENT; ADDITIONAL TIME IS NEEDED TO INCORPORATE THE BORN DIGITAL ITEMS, MOVING IMAGE MATERIALS, AND REALIA.
Access Restrictions
Night of the Living Dead Shooting Script, 1967 located in Box 21 Item 1 -- is only accessible through the digital reproduction.
Acquisition Information
Acquired from Suzanne Desrocher-Romero, Tina Romero, and Peter Grunwald on April 19, 2019.
Arrangement
The collection consists of records that were maintained by three different individuals. The arrangement reflects the original order of the bulk of the paper-based materials, which was by document type. Whenever possible, materials that were found outside of that filing method were integrated within the established arrangement.
The collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Scripts, circa 1964-2017
II. Production Materials, circa 1962-2008
III. Publicity Materials, 1962-2009
IV. Promotional Materials, circa 1967-2009
V. Legal Documents, 1970-2012
VI. Correspondence, 1970-2012
VII. Photographs, circa 1950s-2017
VIII. Moving Image Media (forthcoming)
IX. Props and Realia, circa 1983-2017 (in-progress)
Scope and Content Notes
The George A. Romero Archival Collection documents the career of the writer and director through scripts, production materials, publicity, promotional materials, props, photos, and audio-visual materials. It contains materials for Romero's most successful films, including Night of the Living Dead and Dawn of the Dead, as well as lesser known or unreleased projects like Jacaranda Joe and The Liberator and numerous unfinished or unfilmed projects. The largest series is devoted to scripts and other writings, covering the entirety of Romero's career, from the early 1960s to the 2010s. Materials devoted to the development and production of these projects primarily come from the latter half of Romero's career, after he began his partnership with producer Peter Grunwald.
Related Material
Daniel Kraus Papers, 1987-2016, SC.2020.01, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Biography
George Andrew Romero was born on February 4, 1940, in the Bronx, New York. A young cinephile with a strong interest in theater, he started making movies as a child with a camera given to him by his uncle. Romero moved to Pittsburgh to attend the Carnegie Institute of Technology (now Carnegie Mellon University) in 1956, where he became involved in the school and the city's theater communities. In 1962, he co-founded The Latent Image, a production company that made a number of TV commercials and industrial films for local and national campaigns. In 1968, using money earned from commercial work and support from Pittsburgh-based investors, Romero directed his first feature film, Night of the Living Dead, on which he also served as co-writer and cinematographer. Filmed in Evans City and other locations in and around Pittsburgh,Night was the first feature film produced in the Pittsburgh area to receive international attention. An unprecedented success for a low-budget film produced outside of Hollywood or New York,Night invented the modern zombie and proved to be a milestone in the history of both the horror genre and American independent cinema, as well as a foundational effort in the establishment of a film industry in Southwestern Pennsylvania. In 1999, Night was added to the National Film Registry by the Library of Congress.
After the success of Night, Romero remained in Pittsburgh, where he would produce and direct films and television until the early 2000s. Following mixed financial returns on his post-Night work, which included a romantic comedy (1971's There's Always Vanilla), a feminist film about witches (Season of the Witch, 1972), a film about a rapidly-spreading deadly virus (The Crazies, 1973), and a vampire film (Martin, 1978), as well as a series of television documentaries about sports figures (The Winners, 1973-1976), Romero returned to zombies for Dawn of the Dead (1978), filmed at the Monroeville Mall in Monroeville, PA. Dawn was quickly acknowledged as a milestone, beloved by horror fans and hugely influential within the genre. The mall became a destination for horror fans and in 2018 a bronze bust memorializing Romero was installed in recognition of the film's enduring popularity and influence.
One of Dawn's most vocal champions was author Stephen King, who collaborated with Romero as a writer and actor on the cult favorite Creepshow (1982), which spawned a sequel (directed by Michael Gornick) in 1987 and a television series (created by longtime Romero collaborator Greg Nicotero) that premiered in 2019 on the streaming platform Shudder.
Romero continued to work in Pittsburgh, including a third "Dead" film, Day of the Dead (1985). He also directed the modern-day Arthurian fable Knightriders (1980), the psychological horror film Monkey Shines (1988), the Dario Argento collaboration Two Evil Eyes (1990), and the Stephen King adaptation The Dark Half (1993). He also co-created the anthology TV show Tales from the Darkside (1983-1988) and co-wrote and produced a remake of Night of the Living Dead (1990), directed by longtime collaborator Tom Savini. In 2000, Romero directed Bruiser in Toronto, Canada, his first movie produced and filmed entirely outside of Southwest Pennsylvania.
Romero would move to Toronto shortly thereafter, where he would direct his final three feature films. These films – Land of the Dead (2005) (set in downtown Pittsburgh), Diary of the Dead (2007) (about a group of University of Pittsburgh film students and their professor), and his final feature, Survival of the Dead (2009) – revisited and, to a certain degree rewrote, the subject of his then-iconic "Dead" trilogy. In the last years of his life, Romero worked on a number of projects, including several unproduced film scripts, the comic books Toe Tags (2004-2005) and Empire of the Dead (2014-2015), and a book that remained unfinished at the time of his death in 2017. That book, The Living Dead, was planned to retell and extend the stories told in his "Dead" films. It was completed by novelist Daniel Kraus and published in 2020.
Romero died on July 16, 2017, after a brief battle with lung cancer. He died with his family nearby while listening to the soundtrack for one of his favorite films, John Ford's The Quiet Man. As an independent filmmaker working outside of the customary centers of production, Romero reached unprecedented commercial, artistic, and cultural success in the horror genre. He brought sophisticated and often hilarious social critique to the genre, with a style that would be foundational for subsequent generations of horror filmmakers. He helped establish a film industry in the city of Pittsburgh, while bringing a Pittsburgh sensibility to movies, grounded in a working-class sense of humor and community. In the words of the Pittsburgh City Paper, "no other major filmmaker has had such a long history in Pittsburgh or shown such devotion to the city." In 2018, on the 50th Anniversary of Night of the Living Dead's premiere at Pittsburgh's Fulton Theatre (now the Byham Theatre), Mayor Bill Peduto honored Romero's legacy by declaring October 1 to be "George A. Romero Day" and declared that Romero "left no doubt that he loved and respected Pittsburgh. The feeling is mutual."
Independent films; Horror Films -- Production and direction; Horror Films; Business correspondence; Horror stories; Personal correspondence; Motion Pictures -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Film -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Newspaper Clipppings; Screenplays; Television Plays; Promotional Materials; Independent Film -- Production and direction -- Pennyslvania -- Pittsburgh; Motion Picture Producers and Directors -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Zombie Films -- Production and direction; Romero, George A.
- Scripts, circa 1964-2017; I.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains screenplays, teleplays, treatments, and prose manuscripts for film, television, and literary works both published and unpublished. Most works are authored by Romero, but the series also includes works written by other authors.
  - Produced Works, 1967-2017; 1.
    Materials in produced works include treatments, drafts, shooting scripts, and manuscripts related to produced or published works in film, television, and literature. All entries are scripts unless otherwise noted. All working titles or alternate titles are noted in [brackets]. Unless otherwise noted, section dates refer to the date of the film's premiere.
    - Night of the Living Dead [Night of the Anubis] [Night of the Flesh Eaters], 1968; 1.
      A horror film about a small group of people attempting to survive in a remote farmhouse as the dead rise to feed on the living around them. Shot in Evans City and Pittsburgh. The film was known as Night of the Anubis and then as Night of the Flesh Eaters during production before being retitled Night of the Living Dead by the distributor. Starring Duane Jones, Judith O'Dea, Marilyn Eastman, Karl Hardman, Judith Ridley, Keith Wayne. Written by John A. Russo and George A. Romero, directed by George A. Romero.
      - Night of the Living Dead [Night of the Anubis] The "Anubis" Script by Jack Russo, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Night of the Living Dead [Flesh Eaters] basement scene script revision pages, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Night of the Living Dead shooting script, 1967 (Box 21, Item 1)
        George A. Romero's shooting script for Night of the Living Dead. Contains extensive annotations, edits, additions, and re-writes made during filming of the movie.
        Access to the original document is restricted due to preservation and condition issues. Researchers are required to view the digital reproduction only.
      - Night of the Living Dead screen transcript, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        With envelope addressed to "Mr. Russell Streiner, from Walter Reade Organization."
      - Night of the Living Dead partial screen transcript, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - There's Always Vanilla, 1971; 2.
      A feature film about a drifter's romance with an actress after moving back home to Pittsburgh. Shot in Pittsburgh. The film was known as At Play with the Angels and then as The Affair at various stages of production and release. It was based on a short film titled Raymond Laine Short Film. Starring Raymond Laine and Judith Ridley (credited as "Judith Streiner"). Written by Rudolph J. Ricci and directed by George A. Romero.
      - There's Always Vanilla script fragment, circa 1969-1971
        Undated and untitled script pages depicting two scenes.
    - Season of the Witch [Hungry Wives] [Jack's Wife], 1972; 3.
      A feature film about a neglected housewife's embrace of witchcraft as a means of empowerment. Shot in Pittsburgh and the city's northern suburbs. The film was known as Jack's Wife during production and retitled Hungry Wives by the distributor. Starring Jan White, Raymond Laine, and Ann Muffly. Written and directed by George A. Romero.
      - Season of the Witch [Hungry Wives] [Jack's Wife], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Season of the Witch [Jack's Wife] (copy 1), March, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Season of the Witch [Jack's Wife] (copy 2), March, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Crazies [Mad People], 1973; 4.
      A science fiction/horror film about a deadly virus that causes the infected to become disoriented and wildly uninhibited and violent before their deaths. Shot in Evans City. Known during development as Mad People and titled Code Name: Trixie during initial release, it was retitled The Crazies for a 1976 re-release. Starring Lane Carroll, Will MacMillan, and Harold Wayne Jones. Written by George A. Romero based on an original script by Paul McCollough and directed by George A. Romero.
      - The Crazies [Mad People] script, October, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - The Crazies Shooting Script in Mylar pages with highlighting and annotation, undated (Box 21, Item 2)
    - The Amusement Park, 1973; 5.
      An educational film that uses an amusement park as the setting for a nightmarish allegory about the perils that face the elderly in contemporary society. The film was commissioned by Lutheran Social Services with the intention to distribute as a means of raising awareness and funds for their activities, especially Meals on Wheels. Shot at the West View Park, north of Pittsburgh. Premiered at the American Film Festival in 1975, with a restoration premiering in Pittsburgh in 2019. Starring Lincoln Maazel. Written by Walton Cook and directed by George A. Romero.
      - The Amusement Park treatment, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - The Amusement Park treatment and scene outline, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Martin [Blood], 1977; 6.
      A horror film about a shy young man afflicted with a disease that forces him to kill people and drink their blood. Shot in Braddock, PA. Early screenplays were titled Blood. Premiered at the US Film Festival (the forerunner of Sundance) in 1977. Starring John Amplas, Christine Forrest Romero, and Lincoln Maazel. Written and directed by George A. Romero.
      - Untitled Story or Treatment begins "The Parkway East was..." apparent early draft of Martin, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Martin [Blood] treatment (4 pages) (3 copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Martin [Blood] treatment, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Martin [Blood] treatment (13 pages) (3 copies), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Martin first draft, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Martin photocopy, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Martin photocopy, includes memo to "Jason", undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Martin (in folder marked "Martin Screen Play - Do not give away"), undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Martin photocopy (missing final 4 pages), undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Martin shooting script in Mylar pages with highlighting and annotation, undated (Box 21, Item 3)
      - Martin manuscript for novel by Susanna Sparrow, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Dawn of the Dead, 1978; 7.
      A sequel to Night of the Living Dead in which four people try to survive the zombie apocalypse inside of a mall. Shot in the Monroeville Mall in the Pittsburgh suburb of Monroeville, PA and surrounding areas. Starring David Emge, Ken Foree, Scott Reiniger, and Gaylen Ross. Written and directed by George A. Romero.
      - Dawn of the Dead first draft treatment (89 pages) (copy 1), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Dawn of the Dead first draft treatment (89 pages) (copy 2), undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Dawn of the Dead first draft treatment (87 pages), undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Dawn of the Dead script with annotations and paste downs, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Dawn of the Dead script, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Knightriders [Knights], 1981; 8.
      A dramatic action film about a modern-day troupe of Arthurian knights who perform on motorcycles at Renaissance fairs. Known as Knights in early screenplays and materials. Filmed in various locations in Southwest Pennsylvania. Starring Ed Harris, Tom Savini, and Patricia Tallman. Written and directed by George A. Romero.
      - Knightriders original first draft (rough), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Knightriders [Knights] rough second draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Knightriders shooting script, February 5, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Knightriders shooting script (Christine Forrest copy with page revisions in back), February 5, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Knightriders [Knights] shooting script, February 5, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Knightriders shooting script (bound in duct tape), February 5, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Knightriders shooting script in Mylar pages with highlighting/annotation, undated (Box 22, Item 1)
    - Tales from the Darkside TV Series, 1983-1988; 9.
      An anthology horror series produced by George A. Romero, Richard P. Rubinstein, and Jerry Golod that aired from 1983-1987. For the show's four seasons, 94 total episodes were produced, including episodes written by Romero, Stephen King, Robert Bloch, Michael McDowell, and Clive Barker.
      - "Trick or Treat" (Pilot, Aired October 29, 1983) first draft (copy 1), July, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - "Trick or Treat" (Pilot) first draft (copy 2), July, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - "Trick or Treat" (Pilot) first draft in Mylar folder (copy 3), July, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - "Trick or Treat" (Pilot) in Mylar folder second draft, July, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - "The Devil's Advocate" (Season 2 Episode 7, Aired November 10, 1985) (copy 1) (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - "The Devil's Advocate" (Season 2 Episode 7) (copy 2), 1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - "The Devil's Advocate" (Season 2 Episode 7) (copy 3), 1985 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - "The Circus" (Season 3 Episode 1, Aired September 28, 1986) first draft (includes memo and copy of short story source material), February 10, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - "The Circus" (Season 3 Episode 1) first draft in Mylar folder (copy 1), February 10, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - "The Circus" (Season 3 Episode 1) first draft in Mylar folder (copy 2), February 10, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - "The Circus" (Season 3 Episode 1) first draft (includes memo with original source short story and revision pages), February 10, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - "Baker's Dozen" (Season 3 Episode 9, Aired November 23, 1986) first draft (includes memo and original short story) (copy 1), March 15, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - "Baker's Dozen" (Season 3 Episode 9) first draft (includes memo and original short story) (copy 2), March 15, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - "Baker's Dozen" (Season 3 Episode 9) second draft (copy 1), March 22, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - "Baker's Dozen" (Season 3 Episode 9) second draft (copy 2), March 22, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Day of the Dead, 1985; 10.
      The final film in the original "Dead" trilogy in which an underground military outpost finds itself wholly isolated from any other survivors. Filmed at locations in Florida and Southwest Pennsylvania. Starring Lori Cardille, Terry Alexander, and Joe Pilato. Written and directed by George A. Romero.
      - Day of the Dead synopsis, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Day of the Dead original script, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Day of the Dead second version first draft (copy 1), 1984 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Day of the Dead second version first draft (copy 2), 1984 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Day of the Dead second version first draft (copy 3), 1984 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Day of the Dead second version first draft (copy 4), 1984 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Day of the Dead second version first draft (copy 5), 1984 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Day of the Dead second version first draft (copy 6), 1984 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Day of the Dead second version third draft revised, August 3, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Day of the Dead script (missing final page), September 5, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Day of the Dead script (copy 1), September 5, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Day of the Dead script (copy 2), September 5, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Day of the Dead third version second draft (copy 1), September 21, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Day of the Dead third version second draft (copy 2), September 21, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Day of the Dead third version second draft (copy 3), September 21, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Day of the Dead script (signed final page) (copy 1), undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Day of the Dead script (signed final page) (copy 2), undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Creepshow 2, 1987; 11.
      A sequel to the anthology horror-comedy Creepshow, comprised of three segments adapting the tone and style of EC horror comics from the 1950s, including "The Raft," based on a short story by Stephen King. Filmed in Southwestern Pennsylvania. Starring Lois Chiles, George Kennedy, and Dorothy Lamour. Written by George A. Romero and directed by Michael Gornick.
      - Creepshow 2 first draft, January 10, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 3)
        includes "Pinfall" segment (adpated from a Stephen King short story) omitted from final film
      - Creepshow 2 second draft (copy 1), undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
        includes "Cat From Hell" segment (adapted from a Stephen King short story) - eventually featured in Tales from the Darkside: The Movie and omits "Hitchhiker" segment
      - Creepshow 2 second draft (copy 2), undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Creepshow 2 second draft (copy 3), undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Creepshow 2 third draft, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
        includes all segments featured in final film; also includes notes from director Michael Gornick
    - Monkey Shines, 1988; 12.
      A horror film about a man who is paralyzed and develops an unhealthy bond with a service monkey. Filmed in and around Pittsburgh, including the University of Pittsburgh campus. Based on a novel by Michael Stewart. Starring Jason Beghe, John Pankow, and Kate McNeil. Written and directed by George A. Romero.
      - Monkey Shines synopsis or overview (no author credit), undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Monkey Shines treatment by Michael Stewart, February, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Monkey Shines treatment by Michael Stewart, March, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Monkey Shines by Michael Stewart first draft, May 15, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Monkey Shines by Michael Stewart second draft, June 10, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Monkey Shines by Michael Stewart third draft, July, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Monkey Shines by Michael Stewart, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - Monkey Shines by Michael Stewart (in envelope stating "First Peter Grunwald Draft"), undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Monkey Shines by Peter Grunwald (in envelope stating "second Grunwald draft") (copy 1), January, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Monkey Shines by Peter Grunwald (copy 2), January, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Monkey Shines by George A. Romero first draft, December, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Monkey Shines by George A. Romero first draft (noted "Orig" on envelope), December, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Monkey Shines by George A. Romero (unspecified draft but noted "Orig" on envelope), undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Monkey Shines interim revisions, February 4, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Monkey Shines interim revisions, February 13, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Monkey Shines by George A. Romero revised draft (copy 1), February 1987 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Monkey Shines by George A. Romero revised draft (copy 2), February 1987 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Monkey Shines by George A. Romero (copy 3), undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Monkey Shines final draft ("Master Copy" noted on envelope) (copy 1), May 1987 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Monkey Shines final draft (copy 2), May 1987 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Monkey Shines final draft (copy 3), May 1987 (Box 11, Folder 6)